Introduction

THE name Haddon is undoubtedly one of those British surnames which are derived from the name of a place. Until about the year 1350 there were very few surnames in use in Britain. A man bore his baptismal name only, and was distinguished from others who bore the same baptismal name by his trade, some personal characteristic, or by his place of origin. Thus, when a man named John went forth from one of the places named Haddon and settled elsewhere, he was known in his new place of abode as John of Haddon. Soon after 1350 the "of" was dropped, and such a man came to be called John Haddon.

There are three parishes in England called Haddon. One of them is in Huntingdonshire, and two—East Haddon and West Haddon—are in Northamptonshire, There are also the townships of Over Haddon and Nether Haddon, in the parish of Bakewell, in Derbyshire. In the latter of these stands the famous Haddon Hall. Further, a Manor of Haddon forms part of the parish of Bampton, Oxfordshire; a Manor of Caundle Haddon is found in the parish of Caundle Stourton, Dorset. It was owned by a John of Haddon at his death in 1302. (Hutchin's Dorset, III p. 665, and the Fine Roll, October 22, 1302.)

In Scotland there is the village of Hadden, in the parish of Sprouston, Roxburghshire, in which, no doubt, the Scotch Haddens had their original home. The most famous of them was probably Sir John Hadden, who fell at the Battle of Dunbar, in 1650.

Here it may be remarked that Hadden is a frequent variant of Haddon in English documents down to modern times. The forms Haden, Haddan and, occasionally, Haddyn are also found; but Haddon is the most frequent of all.

The late Professor W. W. Skeat, in his Place Names of Huntingdonshire, published by the Cambridge Antiquarian Society, of which, by the way, Dr. A. C. Haddon was recently President, gives the following account of the place named Haddon in that county :—" In Saxon times it was called Headdandune. The sense is Headda's down, or in the old Mercian spelling, Hadda's down. The old Mercian Hadda is a known personal name." The same derivation almost certainly holds true of the other villages called Haddon. Each gained its name from its situation on a down, or hill, which belonged to a Saxon named Hadda.

This derivation is strikingly confirmed by the existence—apparently unknown to Professor Skeat—of a hill named Haddon Down Hill a few miles East of Dulverton, Somerset.

The name Hadda also appears in Haddenham, which means "the home of the Haddas" and in Haddington, which means "the town of the Haddings, or children of Hadda"—the "ing" being a patronymic suffix.

The fact that some six or seven places in Britain bore the name Haddon, largely accounts for the wide area over which men "of Haddon" were spread from very early times. But of course most of these emigrants "of Haddon" were not related to one another. Some of those who went forth from the same village may have been related, but by no means all of them.

As early as the 13th and 14th centuries men called "of Haddon " owned land or occupied public positions in various parts of England. For instance, before the year 1316 Haddons owned land at Ilebruer (now Isle Brewers), in Somerset, and Sir Henry of Haddon of that place had married Elianor, daughter of Sir Matthew of Furneaux (Miscellanea Genealogica et Heraldica, 3rd Series, V0l. III, p. 273.). The Patent Roll of June I, 1363, gives a John of Haddon as the King’s Serjeant-at-Arms. The Close Roll of November 6, 1365, records the death of William of Haddon, Abbot of Thorney Abbey, near Peterborough. The Archives of Lincoln Cathedral preserve the Will of John of Haddon, one of its Canons, who died in 1374 possessed of very considerable wealth.

Nearly a hundred years earlier than this last date we find that London had attracted to itself a Haddon—as it has in every subsequent century. In the Will of Dame Cecilia Harding, which was proved in the Court of Hustings, London, on February 22, 1280, occurs the name of "my brother, William of Haddon." This is the earliest mention of a Haddon in any Will.

Perhaps to the same family belonged John Haddon, draper, of London, who died early in 1427. It is a most interesting fact that his Will, proved in the Court of Hustings on March 26, 1427, shows that he lived and died in the parish of St. Brigid (now called St. Bride) in Fleet Street, very near the spot where the Head Office of John Haddon & Co. now stands. This John Haddon was buried in the Church of St. Bride, Fleet Street. Somewhere beneath its floor the dust of his body lies to-day, and every sunny morning the graceful spire of St. Bride’s casts its shadow on the Head Office of the Firm which bears his name, Probably no other Firm in the City of London can claim that a namesake lived 500 years ago almost on the site of its present office.

As we come down to the 16th and 17th centuries, when Wills become more plentiful and Parish Registers begin, we find numerous Haddons spread over many counties. One or two are men of national eminence, several are gentry and clergy, many are yeomen, and some follow humbler occupations.

We will deal first with Sir Richard Haddon, Lord Mayor of London, and his even more famous grandson, Dr. Walter Haddon, and then mention the Haddons who are to be found in various counties.

Autobiography of Walter Haddon.

Mr. Walter Haddon, in early youth, wished to follow the pursuit of Agriculture as his forefathers had for many generations, but circumstances ordained otherwise. In later life, he returned to Agriculture as a hobby, as a breeder of Hunters. In the year 1914, he was successful in taking the Premium 1st prize for Yearling Colts at the Hunter's Improvement Society held at the Agricultural Hall, London. Mr. Walter Haddon, after several trial periods, was eventually on August 1, 1879, apprenticed to the Printing Trade, to a firm at Great Grimsby where he remained until January 1885. During his apprenticeship and afterwards, he acted as a local correspondent and special reporter for various newspapers, and in this connection instituted the daily market report of the Grimsby Fish Market, which has remained a permanent feature of newspaper market reports.

On February 1, 1885 Mr. Haddon migrated to London with very little cash resources and without any commercial friends, but was successful in procuring a variety of situations with a number of printers in various capacities. In course of situation-finding he discovered the Firm of John Haddon & Co. Till then these branches of the family by the long process of years and the differences of occupation had lost sight of each other, and were practically unknown to each other. By the coincidence of being a Printer by training, and requiring a situation, the introduction led to his engagement as an assistant to John Haddon & Co. for a period of two years from January, 1888 to 1900, during which period such arrangements were made that, dating from January 1st 1890, he became Sole Proprietor. The business of John Haddon & Co., at the time of its being taken over by Walter Haddon, was, comparatively speaking, a very small affair—being  mainly limited to Exporting, Printing and General Materials. Mr. Walter Haddon initiated a new branch of the business as advertising agents as well as greatly extending the exporting branch. In the early days of his connection with the Firm, Mr. Walter haddon developed the Publishing side of the business, but in subsequent years disposed of this section. During this period, amongst other achievements, he acted as a Literary Agent for many influential writers, including the late George Augustus Sala. Mr. Walter Haddon discovered the well-known black and white artist Mr. Phil may, who at the time was working on the Sydney Bulletin.

On the invitation of Mr. Walter Haddon, it was arranged that Mr. Phil May should return to England, and until his death, at an early age, the two were great friends. The worldwide known publication, Phil May's Annual was one of the results of this friendship. Another literary venture was the Butterfly, a monthly publication started by a coterie of well-known artists for artists, the chief of their number being Mr. Raven Hill, who subsequently became a member of the Punch staff. For over 20 years Mr. Walter Haddon was associated with the late Mr. W.T. Stead in The Review of Reviews.

In January, 1897, he started the Caxton Type Foundry, of which a description is given under the account of the Centenary of the Firm. Later on in his commercial career, Mr. Walter Haddon became actively associated with a number of patent devices connected with engineering. This development was the outcome of his purchasing the controlling interests of W. H. Dorman & Co. Ltd., of Stafford, well-known as machine tool makers of high repute, and specialists in the designing and manufacture of Internal Combustion Engines. (During the Great War, this firm played their part by producing, in large quantities, Machiner for the Manufacture of Munitions of War, and was one of the Government Controlled Engineering Works.)

The patents referred to comprised a variety of commercial subjects, and amongst their number, "Vislok", a Safety Lock Nut. Another, and equally successful patent was the vaporization of paraffin for Internal combustion engines. The development of this was a tedious experiment, but eventually it proved a valuable success.

In engineering and scientific circles, unquestionably, the name of Mr. Walter Haddon will always be associuated with that of his colleague and partner, Mr. George Constantinesco, the discoverer and inventor of Wave Transmission.

The discover of Wave Transmission marks a distinct era in the progress of applied mechanics. The problem how to transmit and apply created power, by cheap and simple appliances, to its desired destination, and to do so efficiently and reliably has always been the dream and ambition of inventors, physicists and engineers, and has been the subject of innumerable patents dating from the discovery of steam power. Wave Tra

The Centenary of John Haddon & Co.

SOME idea of the origin and history of John Haddon and Co. will have been gathered from the Brief Accounts of its founder and his two successors. But the fact that the firm celebrated its Centenary in 1914 seems to call for a somewhat fuller description of its career.

It was started in 1814, as purely a printing business. Among other things, Mr. John Haddon used to print the Official Reports of the Baptist Missionary Society. This brought his name before the Baptist Missionaries abroad, and they began to ask him to export to them any religious literature that they might require. It was but a step further to ship other goods along with religious works. Then gradually others, besides Baptist Missionaries, began to apply to Mr. John Haddon to send them goods. Thus a general export trade was built up. It has grown steadily until to-day the Firm acts as a buying agency for goods of every conceiveable character, and exports them to all parts of the civilised world; and to many parts of the uncivilised. All kinds of commissions are carried out for merchants and planters in India, Ceylon, Malay States, China, Japan, Australasia, Africa, South, Central, East and West ; the West Indies and all parts of North and South America. From the early days of its existence, the Firm has also been importers of produce from the British Colonies, especially from the West Indies. That business has also expanded with the passing years, till now its imports come from as many lands as its exports reach.

It must not, however, be suposed that the Firm has allowed its activities as a carrying Agency to deprive it of prominence in the printing trade. On the contrary, it has shown even greater development, especially in the last twenty-five years, in its original metier of printing, or rather in the ancillary branch of type-founding. This department was created by Mr. Walter Haddon, on January 1, 1897, and was commenced iat 96a, Old Street, St. Lukes, E.C., and removed, in 1898, to Market Harborough, in Leicestershire.

There he erected the Caxton Type Foundry—a very extensive set of premises, constructed on up-to-date lines as a model factory. The latest kinds of typemaking machinery are there at work in airy, well-lighted workshops, which are provided with every convenience and comort for the employés. It was the fisrst British foundry to be established for casting British type on the American point system, which ensures exact uniformity in size of the type bodies. Such uniformity can be attained only by very scientific methods of manufacture, involing the most exact measurements down to the one-thousandth part of an inch. Mr. Walter Haddon created a revolution in the British Printing Trade by this introduction of the Point System, and in spite of virulent opposition, amounting at first to a boycott of his Firm by the older Type Foundries, he has lived to see it win its way into general use. The Times in its special issue of  Tuesday, September 10, 1012, on the Art of Printing, referred to Mr. Walter Haddon's initiative work as follows:—

"Previous to the introduction of the Point System, the standard for size of type in England was far from uniform amongst the different founders—the same being the same with regard to the position of the line—and the forst type cast on this system was gradually making its way from America and Germany, and having to face, if not absolute opposition on the part of English makers, at least a very cold welocme, when the question of standardization of point and line was taken up upon a practical and commercial scale, and with great determination in face of many difficulties, by Mr. Walter haddon of the Caxton Foundry. This reformer's case has been different from that of most advocates of improvement, for he lives to see the almost universal adoption of the Point Body and the Point Line, which he championed."

Akin to typefounding, and necessary for the production of illustrated literature, is the manufacture of zinc and copper plates for etchings and engravings. This industry was almost entirely in the hands of American and German Firms until, in 1912, John Haddon & Co. opened Works at Clapham, S.W. The plates turned out there have largely ousted those of foreign manufacture, and the Firms Centenary saw the capaxcity of the works in process of being doubled.

The Lord Mayor of London, opening the International Printers' Exhibition, held in London, in May 1914, prefaced his speech by saying:—

"Perhaps he might be pardoned the personal mention that it was of great interest to be conducted through Haddon Hall, and to meet his old friend and acquaintance, Mr. Walter Haddon. He was very pleased indeed to find what an important personality in the craft Mr. Haddon had become, and what a large exhibit he made."

Another of the manifold activities of John Haddon & Co., which the Centenary saw in full swing, is the Advertising Agency. This, like other departments of the business, has its roots far back in the Firm's history, but its chief growth has been manifest in recent years.

The results that this brief sketch shows to have been attained by a hundred years of ever-widening activity, cannot but redound to the credit of all who have contributed to them.  But history should beget history, and teh past prove an incentive to the future. As Virgil of old sang, Labor omnia vincit (Labour conquers all things), and in view of the great fields of achievement that lie open to progressive men of business to-day, John Haddon & Co. will not, like Alexander the Great, sit still and sigh that "There are no more worlds to conquer."

A Short Description of the Village of Naseby

"Few spots of ground in all the world are memorable to an Englishman."—Thomas Carlyle.

At this point where our narrative practically ceases to mention Naseby, some account of this historic village seems appropriate. It will no doubt be of interest to those members of the family who have never visited their ancestral home, and particularly to the 47 Haddons, and the 13 descendants of Haddons down the female line, who are mentioned in this book as now living in our Colonies. Naseby is a picturesque village that stands perched amid the uplands of North-western Northamptonshire. The weathercock on its church spire is the highest thing in the county, being about 760 feet above sea level. Thence on a clear afternoon the sun's rays can be seen shining on the North Sea, some 60 miles away.

When John Haddon, whose life has just been related, and his ancestors farmed at Naseby, the parish was still an "open field" with no hedges, few trees, and roads that were mere cart tracks across the land; and this state of things lasted till 1822. All the houses, save three or four, were built of the tenacious Upper Lias clay mixed with straw-as they still were in 1842 when Thomas Carlyle visited the village. His terse words give us a vivid picture:

"The old hamlet of Naseby stands yet, on its hill top, very much as it did in Saxon days —-a peaceable old hamlet, with clay cottages for labourers, but neatly thatched and swept; smith's shop, saddler's shop, beer shop, all in order, forming a kind of square which leads off southwards into two long streets; the old church with its graves stands in the centre."

But now at Naseby, as elsewhere, "old times are changed, old manners gone." A new inn and new smith's shop, of staring brick, replace what Carlyle saw, though the old saddler's shop fortunately remains to form a thing of beauty at the Western entrance of the village. The rest of the thatched clay cottages, with five or six exceptions, have given place to those of brick. Most of these have those "roofs of slated hideousness" so hateful to Tennyson; but along the road from the East towards the Church and the Manor House where John Haddon lived, there have been built picturesque red tiled cottages with pleasant gardens round them. The stately Church with great century-old chestnut trees half encircling it, and the glorious Tithe Barn hard by, built, in 1651, of huge oak beams with intervening panels of lath and plaster dappled with moss, combine to form as attractive a picture as any English village can show.

The fact that Shakespeare's Avon has its source at Naseby has been stated on the previous page. In Edward FitzGerald, Naseby may claim a connection with another poet, as mentioned on page 23.

Naseby's chief renown rests, of course, on the famous Battle of Saturday, June 14, 1645, when the army of Charles the First "after three hours' fight, very doubtful"—as Oliver Cromwell himself wrote the same evening—was broken by the larger forces (nearly two to one), of Generals Fairfax and Cromwell. It is impossible here to give an adequate account of the battle, that decided the downfall of the King's cause. The positions of the two armies on the field are known almost to a yard, and several large graves, where the slain were buried together, can still be seen with their mounds sunk into hollows, and occasionally bullets are still turned up by the plough.

A Brief Note About Mr. F. W. Haddon.

When little over twenty years of age, Mr. F. W. Haddon became Assistant Secretary of the Statistical Society and Institute of Actuaries, London. In 1863, he went out to Australia as private Secretary to Mr. Edward Wilson, the Senior Proprietor of The Melbourne Argus, and shortly afterwards became the first Editor of The Australasian. In 1867, he was appointed to the very important post of Editor of The Melbouren Argus, being only twenty eight years old. He occupied the Editorial chair for no less than 31 years, fully maintaining the high position of that Paper. Two of the chief aims of his Editorship were to urge the desirability of Australian federation, and to preserve intact the Second Chamber, called the Legislative Council, of Victoria. He lived to see both these objects successfully accomplished. On his retirement from the Editorship in 1898, he was placed on the Proprietary Board of his Paper as the Edward Wilson Representative, and held that position till his death, which occurred after a very short illness.

Mr. Haddon possessed a dispassionate mind and clear insight. with imperturbable temper he kept steadily to any course that he had decided was right. He had a marked gift for discovering promising talent, and for bringing out the best powers of his subordinates, and won the affection as well as the respect of his Staff.

John Haddon of Finsbury and Upper Tooting.

Mr. John Haddon, the eldest son of the founder of John Haddon & Co. by his second wife, was born in City Road, London, on May 1, 1823. After being educated at University School, he helped his father in his business for a time, and on April 4, 1843, he became apprenticed to “John Cross, Citizen and Stationer of London”, as his indenture expresses it.

After his apprenticeship he joined his father's firm, and at his death in 1855, he became the proprietor. In 1857 the Firm moved from 24, Castle Street, Finsbury to 3, Bouverie Street. A branch was opened in Budge Row in 1871, and moved to Leadenhall Street in 1873. Previous to this, about 1868, Mr. Haddon had taken Mr. James Watchurst as partner, and the firm then became John Haddon & Co. Mr Watchurst withdrew about 1871, and Mr. Haddon conducted the business by himself for some ten years. After that, Mr. W.O.E. de Hellinger Löhnstein became partner for a time. in 1888 Mr. Haddon's second cousin, Mr. Walter Haddon, joined the Firm, and when Mr. Haddon retired he became its head.

Mr. Haddon had several hobbies in life. He inherited his father's love of music, and was a player of the violincello. Like his father, Mr. Haddon found his musical gifts useful in his business. He published several hymn and tune books, notably, The Psalmist and Psalms and Hymns. As a youth, Mr. Haddon was an enthusiastic cricketer, and he kept up his interest in the game to the very end of life. Gardening was also one of his hobbies.

Mr. Haddon took much interest in the welfare of working men, encouraging them to attend classes for ambulance work, and for general self-improvement. Mr. Haddon was also one of the first in the City of London to employ women in counting-house work.

Mr. Haddon's religious life was very real and thorough. For many years he was a deacon at the various Chapels which he attended. He took great interest in Sunday School work, being himself an active teacher up to the age of 70.

After a brief and painless ilness, the result of a chill, Mr. Haddon passed away on Dec. 10, 1904, aged 81, and was laid to rest beside his gifted wife. Her literary works are enumerated on page 70 under her nom de plume, Caroline Hadley. On page 61, are given brief notices and photographs of their two gifted sons.

History of John Haddon, the Founder of John Haddon & Co.

MR. JOHN HADDON was born at Naseby on August 7, 1784. His father farmed part of the "Open Field" of Naseby, where the fortunes of King Charles received such a fatal blow on June 14, 1645. Mr. Haddon used to tell his children in after years how, as a boy, he had often picked up on his father's farm bullets that had been fired in the famous battle. His mother was a woman of culture and refinement, and he, no doubt, inherited from her, his decided taste for literature.

Mr. John Haddon received the chief part of his education in Northampton at the school of Mr. Richard Comfield, whose sister afterwards became the wife of Mr. John Haddon's cousin, Thomas Haddon of Olney (see page 36). At the age of 15 Mr. John Haddon was apprenticed to Mr. Morris, a printer at Clipston, near Naseby, with whom he moved to Dunstable towards the close of his apprenticeship. Mr. Morris printed the early publications of the Baptist Missionary Society, and thus his apprentice became well acquainted with the work of that Society, in which he took a great interest all his life. At Dunstable he formally became a member of the Baptist Community.

About 1806 Mr. John Haddon came up to London, where he spent the rest of his life. In 1810 he married for his first wife Miss M. A. Blyth, of Langham, Essex, by whom he had two sons, John, who died in infancy, and Daniel Blyth, whose descendants are set forth on the opposite page.

In 1814 Mr. John Haddon took the most important step of his life in founding the Printing Business that is now known as John  Haddon & Co., and last year celebrated its Centenary. Its birthplace was 12, Tabernacle Walk, Finsbury Square. After a few years it was moved to Castle Street, behind Tabernacle Walk. It started as purely a printing business, and was one of the very few Firms of that day which had a stereotype foundry. Among the various works which it published we can well imagine that its Founder must have taken a special interest in The History of Naseby, his birthplace, the second edition of which was printed and published by him in 1813 for its author, the Rev. John Mastin, Vicar of Naseby.

Mr. John Haddon also printed a considerable amount of religious literature for the Baptists, and particularly for the use of their foreign Missions. When sending such literature abroad, he was often asked by the missionaries to forward other goods at the same time.

Thus began the export trade in general goods which now forms a part of the manifold activities of John Haddon & Co. In 1815 Mr. John Haddon lost his first wife, and for seven years remained a widower.

When he was on a visit to his sister, Mrs. Elizabeth Carryer, at Leicester, Mr. John Haddon became acquainted with Miss Elizabeth Cort, and in 1822 he married her as his second wife. She was the eldest of the four daughters of Mr. James Cort, a Merchant, of Leicester, whose wife had died when her youngest daughter was born. Thus Mr. Cort had the task of bringing up his daughters—a task that he most ably carried out. His wife had been a daughter of the Rev. Thomas Robinson, Vicar of S. Mary's, Leicester, and author of Scripture Characters, a very well known book of that day. A tradition that he was descended from a Lord Grantham, whose family name was Robinson, seems to be unfounded. His father was James Robinson, a woolstapler of Wakefield.

Mr. Cort was wise enough to give them the best education that was then possible. Miss Elizabeth Cort was sent to the famous school kept by Miss Cleobury, at Nottingham, where among other things, she learnt painting from the subsequently noted artist, Bonington, who was Turner's master. It was thus a highly cultured wife, whom Mr. John Haddon took to his home in City Road, London. Soon after the birth of their eldest son, they moved to 25, Tabernacle Walk, Finsbury Square, where, as time went on, three sons and nine daughters were born. A charming picture of their family life, as well as of the careers of their daughters, is drawn in Mrs. Bayne's booklet, Five Sisters and a School, published by Berryman & Sons, Blackheath Road, S. E. There it is shown how keen an interest Mr. and Mrs. John Haddon took in the  philanthropic movements of the time, not least in that for the abolition of slavery. One of their sons was named Wilberforce, after the great abolitionist, William Wilberforce. Many philanthropists and foreign missionaries found a ready and hospitable welcome in that enlightened home. Mr. and Mrs. John Haddon naturally took care that their children had an excellent education, which five of their daughters handed on to numerous pupils in their school at Dover. They all inherited and developed a love of drawing and poetry from their mother, and musical talents from their father who had a fine and cultivated bass voice and a very sensitive ear.

It was, no doubt, his musical gifts that made Mr. John Haddon dissatisfied with the music then used in Baptist Services; and he determined to improve it. For this purpose he brought out, between 1838 and 1842, The Psalmist and The New Selection Hymn Book. These publications at first met with opposition from those who were wedded to the older style of music; but eventually they won wide acceptance, and did much to elevate the musical taste of Baptist congregations. Mr. Haddon also published a considerable amount of secular music. The works which he printed included Dr. Adam Clarke's Bible, and the earlier volumes of the well-known Bohn's Library. He himself was fond of literary work and wrote many articles upon current religious topics for The Baptist Magazine and The Eclectic Review. Not long before his death he composed an essay upon Immortality, which was afterwards published in book form. (See page 70). Though a strong Nonconformist, he was not narrow in his views. He constantly used to say, "I prefer to find points of contact, not of difference, with my fellow Christians."

A Brief Account of Thomas Joseph Haddon of Clipston.

Mr. Thomas Joseph Haddon, the only child of Mr. Joseph Haddon of Naseby, had the great misfortune to lose his father when he was four years old. Mr Joseph Haddon was attacked by illness, and in the hope of a cure, he was taken by his brother John to Folkestone. While he was there he was baptised in the sea, going into the water on crutches. He had a beautiful bass voice, and, so long as strength lasted, he used to assemble young men in his rooms a t Folkestone for musical evenings, he himself playing the flute.

The treatment proved unsuccesful, and he returned home to die. His body was laid to rest in Naseby churchyard beside his father and mother on June 17, 1825. A slate tombstone there still clearly records his death at the age of twenty-nine.

His widow, Mrs. Ruth Haddon with her only son, Thomas Joseph, shortly afterwards removed herself to her native village of Clipston, three miles from Naseby, where her husband had held the farm formerly cultivated by his father, Mr. John Haddon of Naseby and Clipston.

This farm, Mrs. Haddon retained—as the Churchwardens' Rate Book at Clipston shows—till on April 3, 1828, she married Mr. John Eaton, of Clipston, as her second husband.

Under their care Thomas Joseph was brought up. He attended the Baptist Sunday School and Chapel, of which his father and grandfather had been Deacons. His religious life all his days centred round the Chapel and its Services, and for thirty-five years he acted as the Superintendent of its Sunday School.

In 1847 Mr Thomas Joseph Haddon married miss Mary Watkins, of Clipston. They had played together as children, and thier married life of nearly fifty years proved as happy to them both as their childhood's hours of play. Eleven children were born to them, and with the exception of one who died in infancy, they were all living at Mr. Haddon's death, and all prospering in various walks of life—two of them helping to build up the Empire in South Africa.

Mr. Haddon followed his ancestors' profession of agriculture, being tenant of their Clipston Farm, which is now cultivated by his son, Mr. Joseph Haddon, and has thus been held since 1815 by four generations of Haddons, and will in due course be occupied by his son John, a member of the fifth generation, who is now associated with his father in farming it

Mr. Haddon's hand was ever generous towards the poor in the village. He served their interests well as a Guardian and a Trustee. After an illness of several months, Mr. Haddon passed away on September 11, 1893, at the age of 72, and was laid to rest in the Graveyard of the Chapel which he loved so well.

Thomas Robinson Haddon (page missing)

'successful' man. He had qualities of mind and soul which shut him out of the limelight. But he was one of the leavening forces which have served to purify colonial life, to widen its visions, to uphold its ideals, and give moral quality to its movements. Men have died for South Africa; he lived for her. Some have used South Africa as a stepping-stone to personal advancement or vulgar self-advertisement. He was one of those hidden hosts who flung soul and body down to be ploughed into her soil and enrich her for all the ages to come. How he loved South Africa, revelled in her beauty, wrestled with her problems, shared her crusts, and gloried in her future! Ah me! That we had more like him! I knew him in his home, in Johannesburg, a home which in that city of the Homeless gathered about it all the charm of an English fireside, and all the freedom of an African stoep. I knew him as a refugee in Durban in the dark days, keeping through all a gaiety of soul, and a sweetness of temper. I knew him amidst the hurly-burly of the Rand, and have found him, when he was Secretary of the Safe Deposit, watching over his treasure house, there ‘’tween chains,’ but revelling in Browning, or chanting Logfellow and Omar Khayyam! Over his head men watched the markets, and fought for ‘Wild Cats’, but he jangled his magic keys to the music of the spheres, and was gloriously happy over a new book! Truly, as Kipling sings,

On the bones of the English,
The English Flag is stayed.

But surely it is no less on the hears of the English, on their real culture of mind, and on their character-value. There for a life time, in a Land of Expediency, through days of darkened intrigue, in times of panic and passion, through years of drought and dread, of pestilence and many wars—

he bore without reproach
The grand old name of Gentleman !

I wonder if he had any enemies! I think not, and yet he was not of the weak fraternity of smirk-makers who cannot hate. He wore the white flower, but never the white feather. the past few years brought him grief, and he was sore smitten by the arrows of bitter sorrow. But he wrote to me in the clanging words of W. E. Henley—

In the fell clutch of Circumstance,
I have not winced nor cried aloud.

And now that he rests in the land he loved, and has ‘pass’d to where, beyond these voices there is peace,᾿ we wail no requiem, and cherish no grief. Such a maker of Empire-makers cannot die while the nation he helped to make lives. So I lay this tribute to his grave, and in words he often quoted from Browning’s ‘Grammarian’—

Leave him–still loftier than the world suspects
Living and dying."

Brief Account of William Haddon of Hollowell

THERE is a family tradition that in his early youth William Haddon went from his home at Naseby to Yorkshire, accompanied by his brother John, the grandfather of Mr. John Haddon, who in 1814 founded in London the Firm of John Haddon & Co., which last year celebrated its centenary. The object of their journey was to purchase unbroken horses, which on their return they sold in Northamptonshire, and with the profits took farms—John at Naseby, and William at Hollowell, a hamlet in the parish of Guilsborough, some five miles south of Naseby. There seems no reason to doubt the truth of this old family tradition. just before he settled at Hollowell, William Haddon married Miss Sarah Langley of Clipston, a village adjoining Naseby. The family of Langley had long held a good position there. We find, for instance, that Augustus Langley, "yeoman of Clipston," was Patron of the Rectory of the adjacent parish of Great Oxendon in 1623.

The children of William and Sarah Haddon were all baptised at Guilsborough Church, except Thomas, the youngest, who was born in 1775. This fact is interesting, for it gives us the approximate date when the Haddons of Hollowell left the Church of England and became Baptists. Their grandson, the late Rev. T. C. Haddon, for 45 years Vicar of Tunstall, Norfolk, has left on record the reason for this change of belief It appears that they and some other inhabitants of Hollowell and Guilsborough found little profit in the ministrations of the Rev. John Bullivant, Vicar of Guilsborough, and consequently went to Creaton Church, where the Vicar, Mr. Maddock, was a noted preacher. When he left Creaton, the Haddons and their friends, not liking his successor, built a Baptist Chapel at Nortoft in Guilsborough, with land for a graveyard behind it.

The Haddons became intimately connected with members of the Baptist community at Guilsborough through the marriages of their daughters. Anna Haddon married William Pell, a tallow chandler, and Elizabeth Haddon married Richard Harris, a baker. The families of Pell and Harris were both Baptists, as gravestones in the Baptist Burial Ground at Guilsborough abundantly testify. In fact, one of the ministers of the chapel belonged to the family of Harris. In that graveyard, William Haddon saw his wife laid to rest in 1798, and his son Edward seven years later. In 1806, William Haddon himself was buried in the same quiet spot. To their memory was erected a slate tombstone, which stands to-day (1915) with its well-preserved words:—

"In Memory of William Haddon, who Departed this Life October 31, 1806. Aged 71.
Also Sarah his Wife, who died November 10, 1798. Aged 60.
Also Edward Haddon, their son, died July 27, 1805. Aged 34."

It would appear that William and Sarah Haddon were conspicuous for their strong religious convictions, and lived honourable and industrious lives, bringing up their children well. Their daughters married respectable tradespeople of the same religious views. Three of their sons appear to have been living in Guilsborough when William Haddon made his will in 1801. But their youngest son, Thomas Haddon, had then removed to Olney in Buckinghamshire. He was the genius of the family, and his children and grandchildren have shown considerable intellectual gifts. But the story of his life demands separate treatment.